所以今天的课，今天的阅读有两个主题。
So today's class, today's reading has two topics in it.
我们将讨论静态类型，更一般地说，
We're going to talk about static typing and, more generally,
静态检查。
static checking.
我们要把它和三大地产联系起来
We're going to relate that to three big properties
好的软件是最重要的信息
of good software that are the essential messages
是这个班的。
of this class.
作为一个运行示例，让我们讨论一个特定的序列
As a running example let's talk about a particular sequence
被称为冰雹序列的数字。
of numbers called the hailstone sequence.
定义如下。
It's defined as follows.
所以如果你从一个整数n开始。
So if you start with an integer n.
然后冰雹序列中的下一个数字，
Then the next number in the hailstone sequence,
这取决于n是偶数还是奇数。
it's going to depend on whether that n is even or odd.
如果是偶数，那么下一个数就是n除以2。
If it's even, then the next number is just n divided by 2.
如果它是奇数，那么下一个数字是3乘以n加1。
If it's odd then the next number is 3 times n plus 1.
你停下来，序列结束，当它达到1。
And you stop, the sequence ends, when it reaches 1.
下面是一些例子。
So here's some examples.
如果你从2开始，那就扯平了，
If you start with 2, that's even,
把它除以2，得到1，序列就停止了。
and so you divide it by 2, you get 1, and the sequence stops.
如果你从3开始因为这很奇怪，
If you start with 3 because that's odd,
三倍，加1。
you triple it, and add 1.
下一个数字是10。
So the next number is 10.
现在已经扯平了。
That's now even.
所以你除以2。
So you divide by 2.
你降到5，这很奇怪，所以你把它翻了三倍。
And you go down to 5, which is odd, so you triple it.
加1。
And add 1.
到16岁。
And you get to 16.
然后你除以2，除以2，除以2。
And then you divide by 2, divide by 2, divide by 2.
当你到达1时，你终于停下来了。
And finally you stop when you get to 1.
事情就这样继续下去。
And things continue like that.
例如，你会注意到
And you'll notice, for example, that whenever
你在冰雹序列中达到2的威力，
you reach power of 2 in a hailstone sequence,
你很快就会除以2，然后再往下看
you're going to very quickly divide by 2, and drop back down
然后用1完成这个序列。
and finish the sequence with 1.
但其他种类的数字，其他起始数字，
But other kinds of numbers, other starting numbers,
可能更令人惊讶的是序列的行为。
may be much more surprising how the sequence behaves.
所以，如果你从7开始，你会有很多反弹。
So if you start with 7, you bounce around a lot.
现在还不清楚这会在哪里停止。
And it's not even clear where this is going to stop.
有一个公开的推测冰雹序列总是
There's an open conjecture that the hailstone sequence always
最终达到每n开始1。
eventually reaches 1 for every starting n.
但这仍然是一个悬而未决的问题。
But that's still an open question.
这叫做冰雹序列，
It's called a hailstone sequence,
顺便说一下，因为云中有冰雹
by the way, because hailstones in clouds
通过上下跳动逐渐形成
form by bouncing up and down, gradually
建造足够重量的冰直到它们落到地面。
building enough weight of ice until they fall down to earth.
所以这是个很好的比喻
So that's sort of a nice metaphor
因为你在想这个。
for thinking about this.
现在我们要考虑的原因是
Now the reason we want to think about it
因为冰雹序列是一个很好的方法
is because the hailstone sequence is a nice way
考虑比较Python和Java。
to think about comparing Python and Java.
所以这里有一个Java程序可以计算
So here's a Java program that computes
冰雹序列从一个特定的n开始。
the hailstone sequence starting from a particular n.
在这种情况下，n等于3。
In this case n equals 3.
这是同一个Python程序
And here's the same Python program
从同一个号码开始。
that starts at the same number.
你会发现有些相似之处
And you'll notice there's some similarities
Java和Python的语法也有一些不同。
and there's some differences between Java and Python syntax.
一个很大的相似之处是
One big similarity is that the major statements
以及主要的运算符和表达式
and the major operators and expressions
基本上是一样的。
are basically the same.
所以Java中的while语句与while非常相似
So a while statement in Java is very similar to a while
Python中的语句。
statement in Python.
它有一个条件，每次你测试
It has a condition that's tested every time you
绕圈子走。
go around the loop.
只要条件是真的，你就继续循环。
And as long as that condition is true, you keep looping.
类似地，if语句有test。
Similarly an if statement has test.
如果这个测试是真的，你会做些什么。
It has something that you do if that test is true.
它可能还有其他的东西
And it may have an else, which is something
如果那次测试是假的，你会的。
you do if that test is false.
但也有一些战术上的差异。
But then there's some tactics differences.
例如，Java要求您有一个分号
So, for example, Java requires that you have a semicolon
在每句话的结尾。
at the end of every statement.
而Python只允许您换行。
Whereas Python just lets you put in a line break.
类似地，Java要求
Similarly, Java requires that there
在while语句中用括号括住这些条件
be parentheses around these conditions in while statements
以及if语句。
and if statements.
所以这些括号是必需的。
So these parenthesis are required.
它们在Python中是可选的。
They would be optional over here in Python.
最后。
And, finally.
Java使用花括号来表示
Java uses curly braces to indicate
while循环中的语句块
the block of statements that is inside a while loop
或者在if语句或else块中。
or that is inside an if statement or an else block.
当然，在Python中，这是用冒号表示的
And in Python, of course, that's signaled by a colon
然后通过缩进
and then by indentation that groups
这些声明在一起。
those statements together.
就Java而言，这些花括号
As far as Java is concerned, these curly braces
足以告诉你在哪里
are enough to tell you where the block of statements
while循环的开始和结束。
of the while loop begins and ends.
这里的凹痕实际上是不相关的。
This indentation here is actually irrelevant.
我可以用Java把这些行排成一行
I could in Java line up all of these lines
与左边距齐平，程序
flush with the left margin, and the program
仍然会以同样的方式工作。
would still work the same way.
如果你想在Python中这样做，Python会抱怨的。
If you tried to do that in Python, Python would complain.
但对于人类，对于一个读到这篇文章的程序员来说，
But for human beings, for a programmer reading this,
我们真的还想缩进那个内部块。
we really want to still indent that inner block.
Java不会注意额外的空间，
Java won't pay any attention to that extra spaces,
但它真的会帮助人们认识到
but it will really help a human being recognize
这里有一个街区。
that there is a block here.
所有这些语句都在那个块中。
And that all of these statements are inside that block.
所以编程是一种交流。
So programming is a form of communication.
你不仅仅是在和电脑交流，
You're communicating not just with the computer,
但也和人类，或者和另一个程序员
but also with human beings, either with another programmer
需要阅读这段代码的人，甚至是你自己
who needs to read this code, or even with yourself
稍后当你回来试着理解这个程序。
later on when you come back and try to understand this program.
人类真的需要这个凹痕，
Humans really need that indentation,
所以这将是我们的第一个例子，也是最简单的
so that's going to be our first example and simplest
这门课的主要原则之一的例子。
example of one of the big principles of this course.
使你的程序更容易阅读。
Which is making your programs easy to read.
我们稍后再谈。
We'll come back to that later.